Finding Aid for George Hempl pamphlets and reprints, 1892-1915
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Hempl pamphlets and reprints 1892-1915
Hempl, George, 1859-1921.
1 boxes
752 DA 2; H491.5; P186
Professor of English at the University of Michigan; reprints of articles on various topics in etymology, notably on Old English and ancient Hittite and Ionic Greek.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was assembled from a variety of sources.
No further additions to the collection expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
George Hempl was a professor of English at the University of Michigan.
The Hempl collection consists of reprints of articles on various topics in etymology, notably on Old English and ancient Hittite and Ionic Greek.
Subjects:
Language and languages--Etymology.
- Pamphlets and reprints.
  - The æ/a/v of 'ARE', 'FATHER', 'RATHER'. (American Journal of Philology, October, 1900 ) (Box 1)
  - American Speech-Maps.
    (No publisher, no date)
  - The Calf of the Leg. (Modern Language Notes, May, 1901 )
  - Chaucer's Pronunciation, and the Spelling of the Ellesmere MS.. (D.C. Heath & Co., Boston 1893 )
  - The Duenos Inscription. (Transactions of the American Philogical Association, 1902 )
  - Early Cyprian Greek. (Transactions of the American Philological Association, 1915) ), 2 copies
  - Early Etruscan Inscriptions: Fabretti 2343-2346. (The University Press, Stanford University, California 1911 )
  - The Easiest German Reading for Learners Young or Old: English Nursery Rimes in German, (Ginn & Company, Publishers 1898 )
  - An English Miscellany. (Clarendon Press, Oxford 1901 )
  - English, BEACH, BECK, PEBBLE. (Englische Studien, O.R. Reisland, Leipzig March, 1901 )
  - The English Pronunciation of Greek & Latin Proper Names. (The School Review, University of Chicago Press June, 1898 )
  - The English River-names: REA, REE, RHEE, etc. (Oxford University Press, galley proof 1900 )
  - Etymologies. (American Journal of Philology, 1901 )
  - Etymologies: Cheap, Cope, Coup, Kaupatjan, Caupo,...etc. (2 parts) (Modern Language Notes, November, 1902, December, 1902 )
  - The Etymology of Boss, 'Calf', 'Cow'. (New York Nation, April, 1901 )
  - Germanic Ænas = Old English Ö and Ã; and Vowel-shortening in Primitive Old English. (The Journal of Germanic Philology, 1897 )
  - Grease and Greasy. (Dialect Notes, Modern Language Association of America, March, [1896] )
  - Hickes's Additions to the Runic Poem. (Modern Philolgy, June, 1903 )
  - Hittite Greek: Important Corroboration of The Discovery of the Greek Character of Hittite. (The Nation, September, 1915 )
  - The Hittite Text on The Tarcondemus Boss. (Flugel Memorial Volume, no date )
  - Influence of Vowel of Different Quality. (The Journal of Germanic Philology, 1901 )
  - Is 'Book' From the Latin? (No publisher 1892 )
  - Language-Rivalry and Speech-Differentiation in the Case of Race Mixture. (Transactions of the American Philological Association, 1898 )
  - Learnèd and Learn'd. (Publications of the Modern Language Association of America, no date )
  - The Linguistic and Ethnographic Status of the Burgundians. (Transactions of the American Philological Association, 1909 )
  - Loss of R in English through Dissimilation. (Dialect Notes, 1893 )
  - MISSING Squint and Squinny. (Dialect Notes, 1893 )
  - Middle English-wo-,-wo-. (Journal of Germanic Philology, Vol. I. 1897 correction: Vol. II, 1898)
  - The Misrendering of Numerals: Particularly in The Old English Version of Bede's History. (Modern Language Notes, November, 1896 )
  - The MØJEBRO RUNIC STONE and The Runic Ligature for NG. (Publications of The Modern Language Association, [1900] )
  - OE: RÆSN, REN, ÆRN, HRÆN HRÆN. ([Anglia], 1901 )
  - The Old Doric of The Tell El Amarna Texts, (Transactions of The American Philological Association, 1914 ), 2 copies
  - Old English C, CG, etc. ([Anglia], 1899 )
  - Old English HÆRFEST. (Journal of Germanic Philology, 1902 )
  - Old English Phonology. (D.C. Heath & Co. 1893, 1895 & 1897 ), 3 copies
  - The Old English Runes for a and o. (Modern Language Notes, 1896 )
  - Old English Runic ænipu lufu. (Proceedings of The American Philological Association, 1896 )
  - The Origin of The Latin Letters G and Z and the COCEULOD ORIESO OF THE Salian Hymn. (Transactions of The American Philological Association, 1899 )
  - The Origin of The Runes. (Journal of Germanic Philology, 1899 )
  - Pepper, Pickle and Kipper. (Publications of The Modern Language Association of America, no date )
  - Report of the Secretary of The Phonetic Section of The Modern Language Association of America for the Year 1897. 1897 )
  - Report on the New Phonetic Alphabet. (Appendix Proceedings of the American Philological Association, 1907 )
  - The Runes and the Germanic Shift. (Journal of Germanic Philology, 1902 )
  - The Runic Inscription on The Isle of Wight Sword.
    (no publisher, no date)
  - The Runic Words, Hickes 135. (Englische Studien, O.R. Reisland, Leipzig no date )
  - The Salian Hymn to Janus. (Transactions of The American Philological Association, 1900 )
  - Der See and Die See. (Journal of Germanic Philology, 1898 )
  - The Sexagesimal System and The Cradle of the Aryans. (The Classical Review, November, 1902 )
  - G. SKALKS, NHG. SCHALK, ETC., G. KALKJO, ON. SKÆKJA, OHG. KARL, NHG. KERL, KEGEL, ETC. (The Journal of Germanic Philology, 1897 )
  - SKÆKJA, KARL, KERL, KEGEL, ETC. (The Journal of Germanic Philology, 1898 )
  - The Solving of an Ancient Riddle: Ionic Greek Before Homer. (Harpers Magazine, January, 1910 )
  - Stovepipes and Funnels. (Dialect Notes, [1902] )
  - The Stress of German and English Compound Geographical Names. (Modern Literature, 1897 )
  - The Study of American English. (The Chautauguan, January, 1896 )
  - The Teacher of English and His Attitude Toward His Subject. (Publications of the Modern Language Association of America, 1904, Delivered on the 28th of December, 1903, at the 21st Annual Meeting of the Association)
  - The Three-Year Undergraduate Period as Affecting Our Scholastic Organization. (Educational Review, December, 1897 )
  - The Variant Runes on The Franks Casket. (Transactions of The American Philological Association, 1902 )
  - Wimmers Runenlehre. (Sievers Festband, 1896 )
- Book Reviews
  - An Elementary Old English Grammar. By A. J. Wyatt. From: Neue Philologische Rundschau, ( October, 1899. )